<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The mystery of iniquity discovered to work in the children of disobedience whereby the pretended godliness of schismaticks appeareth to be the greatest ungodliness : in a cathedral-lecture at St. Peters in Exon / by Arthur Bury ...</title>
            <author>Bury, Arthur, 1624-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 90 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30669</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B6198</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43074</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">26753302</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 26753302</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109777</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30669)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109777)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1712:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The mystery of iniquity discovered to work in the children of disobedience whereby the pretended godliness of schismaticks appeareth to be the greatest ungodliness : in a cathedral-lecture at St. Peters in Exon / by Arthur Bury ...</title>
                  <author>Bury, Arthur, 1624-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 31 [i.e. 36], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Francis Eglesfield ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Page 36 misnumbered 31.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109777:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109777:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE MYSTERY OF INIQUITY, Diſcovered to work in the children of diſobedience. Whereby the pretended Godlineſs of <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> appeareth, to be the greateſt ungodlineſs. IN A Cathedral-lecture at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peters</hi> in <hi>EXON.</hi> By ARTHUR BURY M. A Some time fellow of <hi>EXON</hi> Coll. in <hi>OXON.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Cor. 11.13, 14, 15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>For ſuch are falſe Apoſtles, deceitfull workers, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming themſelves into the Apostles of Christ.</p>
               <p>And no marvel, for Satan himſelf is transformed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Angel of Light:</p>
               <p>Therefore it is no great thing if his Miniſters alſo be transformed, as the Miniſters of righteouſneſs, whoſe end ſhall be according to their works.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Francis Eglesfield</hi> at the Marigold in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:109777:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109777:2"/>
            <head>To the Right reverend Father <hi>in GOD JOHN Lord BISHOP OF</hi> EXON, <hi>All ſpiritual and temporal happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs be multiplied.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right reverend in Christ,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the Lord turned away the captivity of our Kingdoms, then were we like men that dreamed: The greatneſs of the felicity, the ſtrangeneſs of the means, the inſenſibleneſs of the manner made us diſtruſt our very
<pb facs="tcp:109777:3"/>ſenſes. When we ſaw the Church immediately after her return from the wilderneſſe, furniſhed with ſuch <hi>burning and ſhining lights,</hi> that it is not eaſily decided whether the promotions or perſons are moſt dignified: then were we like men aſtoniſhed; then did we ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the goodneſs of God, and the force of truth which ſpight of ſo many years perſecutions and tentations, preſerved ſuch multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes undeluded, &amp; uncorrupted. When we heard that your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was appointed to be <hi>the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel</hi> of our <hi>Western</hi> Church, then were we like men tranſported, then did we magnify the Wiſdom of his Majeſty, in committing the government of ſo large a dioceſe to a perſon in whom zeal &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb facs="tcp:109777:3"/>learning &amp; wiſdom, courage and moderation had mingled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into ſo happy a temper, as to render him one of the moſt eminent Patrons of the Church in her affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, &amp; worthy to be numbred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong her moſt eminent paſtors in her proſperity.</p>
            <p>But our wine was cooled with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter when we heard that your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip took too deep apprehenſions of our diviſions, which reſentments will ſoon confeſs themſelves to have abuſed you, when you shall find the far greateſt part of the factious mew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their impudence with their hopes, and forſaking the withered thiſtle for that <hi>tree which though it were cut down yet ſprouteth again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not indeed expectable, but in ſome greater Towns where the
<pb facs="tcp:109777:4"/>wealth, and numbers of their diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſhal tempt them to expect more profit, and reputation from their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy, there will be found ſome ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous ſpirits who will entertain his Majeſties gratious condeſcenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as they did his bleſſed Fathers; that is, as fire doth fuel, not to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, but emboldened; For their obſervation is purblind, who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not that the <hi>Ieſuite,</hi> and <hi>Puritan</hi> agree (as in many other their worſt practices ſo eſpecially) in this, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding all others beſides their own party from any title to heaven, they call a rigid inflexibleneſs, zeal, and Chriſtian moderation, lukewarmnes.</p>
            <p>But if reaſon do not abuſe us we ſhall find, that when mens troubled humors ſhall ceaſe from fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, their underſtandings will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb facs="tcp:109777:4"/>ſo much the clearer for their paſt diſturbances, and able to read thoſe bloudy characters wherein the diſmal effects of Schiſme, are largely written by lamentable experience upon every family of this Nation; ſo that being thus doubly taught, not only by S. <hi>Iames,</hi> but by woful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, they will not hereafter be ſo apt to kindle, if the <hi>Incendiaries</hi> ſhould again ſcatter their <hi>fiery darts</hi> from thoſe miſchievous tongues, which <hi>ſet on fire the courſe of nature and are ſet on fire of Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Towards which conſideration I offered ſome light in this Cathedral which for ſome yeares ſuffered a Schiſme in her very fabrick, by adivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in her body and preachers, and a market in her cloyſtures.</p>
            <p>It was not (ſure) the worthineſs
<pb facs="tcp:109777:5"/>but the neceſſity of the diſcourſe, which moved thoſe hearers to preſs me to this publication, againſt whoſe importunity, I could not harden my ſelf without falling under that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, which I proved to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to them that ſtrive with their ſuperiors.</p>
            <p>And being come ſo far, I was eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly encouraged to make another bold ſtep, and preſent it to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; that the firſt addreſſe which you received in quality of our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, might bring you an omen of good ſucceſs in your charge, an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of the far greater ſervices which you may promiſe your ſelf from many others, equally unknown, but far more able, and an opportunity for an early proof of your goodneſs by pardoning this boldneſs of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordships moſt humbled ſervant. <hi>A. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109777:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IAMES 3.15.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>This wiſdom deſcendeth not (or, This is not the wiſdom which deſcendeth) from above, but is earthly, ſenſual, Divelish.</p>
                  <p>For where envying and ſtrife is, there is confuſion and every evil work (or unſetledneſs and all miſchief.)</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity</hi> wrought in the Apoſtles days,
<note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.7.</note> one of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves complained: but what it was, is it ſelf a <hi>Myſtery.</hi> If we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult their own Epiſtles (which, as they are the <hi>Oracles of God,</hi> ſo muſt needs be the beſt interpreters of the inditers meaning) we ſhall finde great reaſon to conclude that it was the Hereſy of the <hi>Gnoſtiks;</hi> thoſe <hi>falſe Apoſtles, deceitful workers</hi> that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of extraordinary <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> emulated the Apoſtles, peſtered the Church, and ſeduced many of the weaker ſort into faction.</p>
            <p>Of thoſe troubleſome men every Epiſtle complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and this chapter eſpecially ſetteth forth both their <hi>Iniquity</hi> and it's <hi>Myſtery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt he endeavoureth to cool the ambition of their leaders, by ſhewing that the Office of a
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>v.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Teacher</hi> which they ſo greedily ſought, carried with it more danger then honor: and every one had already enough to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>for in many things we offend all,</hi> ſo we need not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame our
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>v.</hi> 2.</note> account. Which it will be extremely dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to avoid when we are Teachers, ſeeing it requireth the greateſt wiſdom and care in the world to keep the <hi>tongue</hi> in order.</p>
            <p>You muſt not judge of the tongue by it's bigneſs;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4, 5.</note>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:109777:6"/>it is indeed little in bulk, but great in effects. The <hi>Bit</hi> is but ſmal in compariſon of the <hi>Horſe,</hi> and ſo is the <hi>Helm</hi> in compariſon of the <hi>Ship,</hi> yet able to <hi>turn thoſe great bodies; ſo is the tongue among the members,</hi> and ſo are the offences and miſchiefs which the tongue draws men into, leaſt in appearance, but greateſt in conſequence.</p>
            <p>From how inconſiderable a ſpark is a whole city brought to aſhes?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 5, 6, 8.</note> How little a quantity of poiſon will infect a whole meſs, and deſtroy a luſty man? Such, ſo deſtructive is the <hi>Iniquity</hi> of the <hi>unruly</hi> tongue.</p>
            <p>It is <hi>as unruly</hi> as pernicious, Man that
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>tameth</hi> or at leaſt <hi>maſtereth</hi> all the ſeveral inhabitants of the air, earth, and water; yet is not ſufficient for this task; ſo we are doubly obliged to beware how we adventure upon that imployment where we ſhall be expoſed to the many temptations of falling into thoſe ſins of an extravagant tongue, whoſe Iniquities are ſo exceedingly, both miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous and inſuperable.</p>
            <p>This may perhaps ſeem a <hi>Myſtery</hi> that there ſhould be ſo vaſt a diſproportion between the bulk and effects of the tongue: But there is yet a greater <hi>Myſtery</hi> behind. Hitherto the fire or poyſon may vye with it: but there is another <hi>myſtery</hi> wherein the whole world cannot match it with a parallel,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>v.</hi> 11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> It is a ridling miſchief. What <hi>fountain</hi> is that <hi>which out of the ſame hole caſteth forth ſalt water &amp; fresh, ſweet water and bitter?</hi> What root is that which beareth branches &amp; leaves of one ſort and fruit of another? What cauſe is that which produceth contrary effects? The Sun indeed hardeneth clay &amp; ſofteneth wax, but he doth not beam out heat and cold; the difference is not in his light, but in the objects which receive it.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>tongue</hi> can at the ſame time <hi>bleſs God and curſe man whom God made like himſelf</hi> and to be loved for his ſake.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 9.</note> You cannot finde in all the creation ſuch another: the <hi>heart</hi> of man it ſelf which is comprehenſive and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful above all things,</hi> yet is deceived if it think it can do this.
<note place="margin">1. John 4.20.</note> 
               <hi>He that loveth not his brother whom he hath ſeen how can he love God whom he hath not ſeen?</hi> The tongue
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:109777:6"/>can really bleſs and curſe: but the heart cannot really, it may feignedly: the love of God if true, will expel the hatred of our brother, if this dwell there, the other will not; however the ſtock and branches and leaves ſpeak a <hi>Fig,</hi> yet the fruit declares an <hi>Olive.</hi> Talk of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and extraordinary gifts? and yet ſtir up <hi>Diviſions</hi> in the Church? Pretend the <hi>love of Chriſt?</hi> and yet live con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his <hi>Example</hi> and <hi>commands? Theſe things ought not ſo to be.</hi> If you will be Chriſtians indeed, let it be known by your <hi>Love,</hi> let your <hi>Wiſdom</hi> appear by your <hi>meekneſs.</hi> For if you nouriſh <hi>ſtrife and envy,</hi> all your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of religion are but ſpecious <hi>lyes</hi> and vain <hi>brags. Love</hi> is of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>malice</hi> of the <hi>Divel,</hi> Chriſt taught you to <hi>learn of</hi> him to <hi>be lowly and meek and finde reſt,</hi> but fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction deſtroyeth the peace and happineſs of mankind, and therefore, <hi>This is not the wiſdom which cometh from above,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee the greateſt cheat in the world detected and arraigned. In the 15. v. his diſguiſe pull'd off, by ſhewing both <hi>that he is not what he pretendeth,</hi> and <hi>is what he moſt profeſſeth to loathe.</hi> In the 16. <hi>verſ.</hi> he is indicted as the moſt pernicious malefactor in the world.</p>
            <p>Firſt His cheat diſcovered by ſhewing his fountain.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Negatively, <hi>not from above.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Poſitively. <hi>It is earthly,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="2">2. His crime impleaded by diſcovering the ſea of <hi>confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and miſchief</hi> which he bringeth upon the world. And theſe are the two Offices of the 2. verſes of my Text. In proſecution whereof, what ſhall I do? ſhall I exerciſe the ſame vehemence as my Apoſtle doth? I muſt then exſpect to be my ſelf accuſed of contentiouſneſs even while I ſpeak againſt it. Shall I then uſe gentleneſs? I may more juſtly expect to be cenſured as an unfaithful Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitor of the cauſe of God and his Church. I will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor to offend on the better ſide: And if I ſhall then be accuſed of bitterneſs, I will appeal to my Apoſtle who is far more invective: If of coldneſs, I will appeal to him too; who hath taught to beware of ſtrife: ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109777:7"/>I ſhall on the one ſide imitate his ardour, or on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther practice his Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Firſt then for the diſcovery of the fountain, and that Negatively. <hi>It cometh not from above,</hi> cannot ſay to God as <hi>David</hi> did.
<note place="margin">Pſalm 87.7. 1 John 1.5. Chap. 4.8, 16.</note> 
               <hi>All my Springs are in thee.</hi> God is called in the Abſtract <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> He is called <hi>Light</hi> with ſo much ſolemnity as will hardly be matched; and we are told after great preparations, that this is the very ſumme of the Goſpel. He is called <hi>Love</hi> twice in one Chapter of the ſame Epiſtle. And they very well ſet forth each other.</p>
            <p>The proper Office of <hi>light and Love</hi> is to reconcile the greateſt enemies, multiplication and union. They are both the greateſt multipliers and uniters. The greateſt multipliers, for it is the proper work of <hi>Light</hi> to <hi>Shine;</hi> that is, to multiply, and furniſh the world with it's ſelf. The Sun is ſuch a Fountain as to ſtream out his light on every little atome of every ſide; and every beam like the Fountain multiplieth into new beams: ſo that whether we believe the Sun to be the Centre of the world, it is admirable that he ſhould extend himſelf to every atome of ſo vaſt a Circle: or, if he be not the Centre, it is yet more wonderful, that his light ſhould reach the moſt diſtant Star and from thence return again to ſhine upon the earth: <hi>Light</hi> is the greateſt, yea and the onely multiplier: every ſeed multiplieth by reaſon of a ſpark of aſtral fire kindled in it, which if it might be husbanded would fill the whole world with it's po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity: As <hi>Light,</hi> ſo <hi>Love</hi> too is <hi>ready to diſtribute, willing to</hi> communicate.</p>
            <p>Again, the beams of light do ſo ſcatter themſelves abroad as to keep cloſe together; not the leaſt piece of the air, where they do not embrace each other, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſome groſs body force a ſeparation; and even then they uſe all poſſible diligence to meet again. And this doth <hi>Love</hi> too, <hi>If it be poſsible, as much as in it lyes, lives peaceably with all men.</hi> Thus <hi>light</hi> which <hi>Plato</hi> well ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by calling it <hi>the shadow of God,</hi> ſetteth forth the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109777:7"/>Divine <hi>Love</hi> in it's two great effects, <hi>liberality</hi> and <hi>peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs.</hi> Which will more particularly appear if we conſider him manifeſted in each office of the three perſons. As <hi>creator, redeemer and ſanctifier,</hi> we ſhall finde that <hi>Love,</hi> not <hi>ſtrife,</hi> cometh <hi>from above</hi> from the <hi>Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, As Father and creator, <hi>God is light,</hi> and being ſo, multiplied himſelf in begetting a world from himſelf. <hi>Love</hi> was the procatartik, <hi>Light</hi> the inſtrumental cauſe of the creation. Which the Divine word deſcribeth to have been performed after this manner.
<note place="margin">Geneſ. 1.</note> 
               <hi>In the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning God created the heaven and the earth. The heaven</hi> as the principle of light and heat, and life and beauty and love: <hi>The earth</hi> as the principle of darkneſs and cold and death, and horrour, and hatred: And thus it was.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There was darkneſs over the face of the deep,</hi> vaſt Abyſs: <hi>and the Spirit</hi> of light <hi>moved upon the face of that liquid</hi> Chaos, and in a moment compaſſed it round, and ſo diſtilled it that the purer parts drew toward the light, and the groſſer fled from it: The purer made that <hi>light inacceſsible,</hi> which is the throne of God <hi>the third heaven: and the evening and the morning,</hi> that exalted <hi>light</hi> and that <hi>baffled darkneſs</hi> were <hi>the firſt day.</hi> Then the Spirit <hi>of light</hi> did again diſtil the now darker reſidue of the <hi>Chaos:</hi> and refined its better part into the ethereal heaven, the manſion of the Sun and Stars, but this ſecond days work is not expreſſed to have any bleſſing becauſe the ſecond number breaketh <hi>unity.</hi> The Spirit of <hi>Light</hi> the third time invaded the yet <hi>darker deep</hi> and diſtilled the better part of it into air, the reſt remaining a thick water with a <hi>caput mortuum:</hi> ſo all the darkeſt and horrideſt parts of the <hi>Chaos</hi> flying the <hi>Light</hi> were precipitated to the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, and being not capable or not worthy of a new di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillation, the waters were ſo removed that ſome parts of the earth might receive the <hi>Light</hi> and furniſh bodies for ſuch <hi>living ſouls</hi> as the heavenly influences ſhould kindle. Thus we ſee in the work of <hi>Creation</hi> the beſt ſtill kept higheſt, and all the darkneſs of the Abyſs fled to the Centre.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:109777:8"/>
            <p>And as the world was created; ſo is it ſtill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by <hi>light and love,</hi> which is the univerſall ſoul of the whole, knitting the higher parts with the lower, and maintaining life here with the continual influences from above; and again tying the lower with ſuch a band of love, that all conſpire the mutuall good. This I might largely prove, and confute the vulgar Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy which dreameth of a continual war between the elements, and fancieth privation a principle of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. But I may fear to have already wearied ſome readers with theſe abſtruſer conſiderations. I ſhall only remember this, which every unlearned man may obſerve, That the very air and water have ſo much love as to forget their own intereſt, when a neighbour ſtands in need of their help. <hi>That</hi> will <hi>deſcend,</hi> and <hi>this</hi> will <hi>aſcend</hi> to ſupply a <hi>vacuum;</hi> which is the <hi>communicative part of love:</hi> and again, if the arrow or the ſhip make a violent divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion they preſently haſt to come together again, which is the <hi>unitive part of love.</hi> Only the <hi>earth</hi> is void of both parts of charity, it <hi>will not communicate,</hi> but ſticketh to it ſelf, and as far as it can prevail freezeth the water to the ſame ſelfiſhneſs: nor it <hi>loves not union,</hi> but unleſs it be glued together with ſome moiſture or hindred for want of place, it crumbleth to pieces, and all the love it hath even to it's own children is kindled in it by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences of heaven.</p>
            <p>Thus from the work of <hi>creation</hi> (which ſheweth that as any thing is higher ſo it proportionably is filled with <hi>light &amp; love,</hi>)
<note place="margin">I am. 1.17,</note> it appeareth that <hi>ſtrife</hi> is none <hi>of thoſe good &amp; perfect gifts which are from above and come down from the Father of Lights,</hi> but riſeth from the uncharitable <hi>earth</hi> the ſeat of darkneſs;
<note place="margin">1 Iohn 2.9, 11. Heb. 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>For he that hateth his brother is in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and walketh in darkneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Son the Redeemer of the world is the brightneſs of his Fathers glory the expreſs image of his Perſon. Brightneſs</hi> is ſo expreſly the <hi>image of Light,</hi> that none but Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers know the one from the other, and they tell us that <hi>brightneſs</hi> conveyeth <hi>light</hi> from it's fountain. Chriſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109777:8"/>came from heaven to bring heaven to us and us thither, and he brought <hi>love,</hi> as the means to <hi>reconcile God to us,</hi> &amp; <hi>us among our ſelves.</hi> The angels proclaimed his coming to be for this end that there might be <hi>peace on earth, and good will both towards</hi> and <hi>among</hi> men (the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth both.) This great buſineſs he promoted in all his Sermons and in all his actions, and all his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; in his life, at his death, and after his death. Taught to have a love ſo <hi>extenſive</hi> as to reach our greateſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ſo <hi>intenſe</hi> as that which himſelf exemplifyed, even to <hi>dy</hi> for one another. This was his <hi>old</hi> and his <hi>new,</hi> his <hi>firſt</hi> and his <hi>last,</hi> his <hi>great</hi> and his peculiar and his criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal <hi>commandment.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 13.34, &amp;c. and 15.12, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>By this shall all men know that ye are my diſciples if you love one another.</hi> Every diſciple is known by the caracteriſtical precepts of his Maſter, the <hi>diſciples</hi> of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> by their <hi>ſilence,</hi> the <hi>diſciples</hi> of <hi>Plato</hi> by their <hi>ſublime notions,</hi> of <hi>Zeno</hi> by their <hi>apathy,</hi> of <hi>Moſes</hi> by their <hi>circumciſion,</hi> of the <hi>Sadducees</hi> by their <hi>denying the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> of the <hi>Phariſees</hi> by their <hi>broad phylacteries,</hi> and <hi>mine</hi> by their <hi>love:</hi> Their <hi>love,</hi> which ſhall be more ardent and more large then any other in the world, and that in ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent a degree that <hi>all men,</hi> even of the weakeſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings ſhall ſee and admire it. Mens <hi>goods</hi> are <hi>known</hi> by their <hi>marks,</hi> their <hi>Servants</hi> by their <hi>liveries, ſoldiers</hi> by their <hi>arms,</hi> and <hi>my diſciples</hi> by their <hi>love:</hi> And it ſhall be ſo conſpicuous that <hi>all men</hi> ſhall ſee it. <hi>All men</hi> know the <hi>Sun</hi> by his <hi>light,</hi> and <hi>fire</hi> by it's <hi>heat,</hi> the <hi>Aethiopian</hi> by his <hi>blackneſs,</hi> and the <hi>Camel</hi> by his <hi>bunch, and all men shall know my diſciples by their love.</hi> Thus was love Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, his proper and peculiar commandment. It was his commandment, and it was his legacy. He left a love-token to be remembred by, which was not only a remembrance of his <hi>love to us,</hi> but an embleme of our mutuall <hi>love</hi> among our ſelfs. The <hi>bread which we break is the Body of Christ,</hi> and teacheth us to remember that <hi>we are one bread and one body.</hi>
               <note place="margin">i Cor. 10.17.</note> The ſame <hi>bread</hi> teacheth that he was <hi>broken</hi> for us, and that we muſt be <hi>knit together</hi> among our ſelves. This is the <hi>wiſdome which cometh from above,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:109777:9"/>brought from heaven by our Saviour, and by him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to us by all poſſible endearments: Thoſe practices which oppoſe this, cannot be the cognizance of Chriſtians, of Antichriſt they may be.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When he left the world he took care to have this his dear <hi>commandment</hi> promoted in his Church by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> which the Apoſtle thus deſcribeth Eph. 4, 8. <hi>When he aſcended on high — he gave gifts to men:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 2.</note> viz. the gift of the holy Spirit (whereby he inſtalled Officers) coming ſolemnly and viſibly upon every of them in the likeneſs of flames of <hi>fire,</hi> which reſemble <hi>cloven tongues</hi> licking the air (the Holy Ghoſt is <hi>Light</hi> too) And theſe Officers were thus inſtalled, that they might kindle in the Church the flames of Divine <hi>Love. That ſpeaking the truth in love,</hi> &amp;c. verſ. 15.16. i.e. That <hi>Love</hi> being the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſoul of the <hi>whole Church,</hi> might <hi>knit</hi> every <hi>ſeveral member</hi> with every other in one common affection, and ſo the <hi>whole body</hi> Eccleſiaſtical <hi>grow up</hi> like a body natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, whereof every member ſhareth with the reſt as in one ſoul, ſo in one intereſt and one affection. To this office they were principally inſtalled and this work they prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally advanced. No duty ſo often, ſo ardently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended as <hi>Love.</hi> If the graces be compared, <hi>the greateſt of them is charity, and above all we muſt have perfect charity.</hi> If their titles be conſidered, <hi>Love is the royal law, the bond of perfection;</hi> If vertues, it <hi>covereth a multitude of ſins, it fulfilleth the law, it is a ſigne of our</hi> intereſt in God. No grace ſo frequently recommended, when there is oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, and when there is none: in ſeaſon and out of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; If <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ies be commended, that faileth not to be in the number; if ſin be condemned, ſtrife is one of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue. If we conſider the meaſure, it is ſet forth by the higheſt compariſons, the love of brethren, and the love of members. <hi>Thus is it done to the</hi> grace <hi>which God delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to honour.</hi> And if the advancement of <hi>Mordecay</hi> be the fall of <hi>Haman; Envy</hi> and <hi>ſtrife</hi> muſt needs be condemned, ſeeing, the wiſdome which is from above doth thus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be as is deſcribed Verſ. 17.18. <hi>Firſt pure, then peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:109777:9"/>&amp;c. Where again you find love exalted; one word for <hi>purity,</hi> but many for <hi>love,</hi> to daſh the impoſtor quite out of countenance and bafflle all his pretences to a heavenly originall. Which cheat is further conſidered.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Poſitively from whence it doth come, which is ſet down to be a threefold foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, It is
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Earthly.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Senſuall.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Divelish.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Which that we may underſtand we are to conſider that we have a threefold life.</p>
            <p>Firſt we live the life of <hi>vegetables:</hi> when we have on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>nourishment and growth</hi> in our mothers wombs.</p>
            <p>Then we live the life of <hi>animals,</hi> when we have <hi>ſenſe and motion,</hi> and laſtly the life of <hi>man,</hi> when we come to the uſe of <hi>reaſon.</hi> Now the law of <hi>Nature</hi> requireth that every thing ſhould act in the beſt manner it can. From our threefold life therefore we are capable of 3. ſorts of ſin. 1. When we ſuffer our <hi>rational</hi> part to be overborn by our <hi>vegetable</hi> and ſo degenerate from <hi>men</hi> to <hi>trees.</hi> 2. When we ſuffer the <hi>animal</hi> faculty to prevaile, and degrade us from <hi>men</hi> to <hi>beasts.</hi> 3. When our <hi>rational</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty ſuffers a defacing of the image of God, and we turn from <hi>partaking the Divine Nature to imitate the Devil.</hi> To one or other of theſe, all ſins are reducible; but fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiouſnes hath this ſingularity that it is guilty of <hi>all</hi> three; A tranſcendent ſin, runs through <hi>all</hi> predica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is <hi>earthly. Earthly mindedneſs</hi> properly taken, is that ſin which turns us to <hi>trees.</hi> Now a <hi>tree</hi> is a man reverſed, hath it's head in the earth, and kicks with it's lower parts againſt heaven. For we are miſtaken if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> take the boughs of a tree to grow upon it's <hi>head:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat is the <hi>head</hi> by which it <hi>feedeth,</hi> thoſe it's lower parts by which it <hi>generateth.</hi> This then is the life of a <hi>tree:</hi> It thruſts the <hi>head as deep</hi> as it can into the <hi>earth,</hi> compaſſeth as much of it as it can with all the roots it can make: whereas <hi>man</hi> is erect, his <hi>head</hi> lifted up to <hi>heaven</hi> and though the weight of his body keep him down to the ground, yet
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109777:10"/>he converſeth with it only with his feet, he trampleth upon it, and bears up from it, and alwayes ſeeketh to enjoy the light and influences of <hi>heaven.</hi> His <hi>affections</hi> are <hi>ſet on things above,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>his converſation is in heaven,</hi> and he is aſhamed of that neceſſity which maketh him beholden to the earth for his maintenance, and <hi>uſeth the world as if he uſed it not.</hi> So that the life of a <hi>godly</hi> differeth from that of an <hi>earthly</hi> man, juſt as a <hi>man</hi> doth from a <hi>tree,</hi> and it is the ſin of earthly-mindedneſs that maketh him thruſt his affections into the things of this world.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>covetouſneſs</hi> is call'd <hi>earthly-mindedneſs</hi> from the object of it's affections: It may deſerve that title upon another reaſon, becauſe as it loveth the earth, ſo it imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tateth it alſo. The <hi>heavenly</hi> bodies are <hi>communicative,</hi> their motion is from the centre to the circumference; the <hi>earth</hi> is <hi>attractive</hi> from the circumference to the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, <hi>thoſe ſend abroad</hi> their light and influences, <hi>this draweth home</hi> to it's ſelf whatſoever cometh within the Sphere of it's activity. That which we call <hi>heavineſs</hi> in maſſive bodies is not ſo truly a quality inherent in them as a neceſſity imprinted upon them, they do not ſeek the earth, but that great Magnet draweth them, The ſame is the difference between the heavenly and the earthly mind. <hi>That,</hi> is liberall; like God and (his type) the Sun, which ſtill beam abroad their bounty: This is greedy, like the earth which ſtill draweth to it's ſelf.</p>
            <p>That <hi>factiouſneſs</hi> is guilty of this ſin, the Apoſtle doth not only <hi>diſcover,</hi> but earneſtly <hi>beſeecheth</hi> to obſerve it. Rom. 16.17. <hi>I beſeech you brethren, mark</hi> (as from a watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tower <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) that you may be forewarned of <hi>thoſe who contrary to the doctrine which you have been taught</hi> bring in ſtrife into the Church in ſtead of the <hi>Royall Law</hi> of <hi>Love;</hi> and under color of <hi>zeal</hi> for Chriſt advance their own <hi>wealth,</hi> Their <hi>fair words</hi> are but alluring baits to draw in the <hi>ſimpler</hi> ſort of people, who cannot ſee through their practices. And <hi>I beſeech you mark</hi> how this
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:109777:10"/>obſervation of the Apoſtle hath been verified among us. The eldeſt cannot remember when firſt <hi>faction</hi> ſet up it's <hi>trade,</hi> and the youngeſt will not ſee it leave its <hi>trade;</hi> and they muſt be very <hi>ſimple</hi> that do not obſerve what a gainful <hi>trade</hi> it hath been and how greedily followed. And who knoweth but God hath ſuffered it to thrive ſo long that we might the more plainly diſcover it, to <hi>love the Houſe of God,</hi> as Ahab loved Naboths Vineyard? for at laſt when opportunity ſmiled upon their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, they ſaid, <hi>let us take to our ſelves the houſes of God in poſſeſsion.</hi> And now we muſt be doubly ſimple if we do not underſtand their true meaning when they ſay they <hi>make God their portion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It is called <hi>ſenfuall</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>animal, brutish.</hi> We know the beaſts <hi>ſeek</hi> no other happineſſe but to ſatisfy the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites of the body: This then is the ſin of <hi>ſenſuality,</hi> when men who are called to <hi>ſpiritual</hi> joyes in the feaſts of a good conſcience and union with God, drown them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in <hi>carnal delights,</hi> gratify the <hi>flesh</hi> and neglect the ſpirit thus degenerating to <hi>beasts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is properly the ſin of debauchery, thus the drunkard and the glutton, the fornicator and the adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer is by all ſober men looked upon as a <hi>beaſt.</hi> But we are further to conſider that there is an <hi>iraſcible</hi> as well as a <hi>concupiſcible appetite,</hi> and all kind of paſſions dwell in the <hi>ſenſual</hi> faculty.</p>
            <p>And though the groſſer ſins of the concupiſcible appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite do in a manner ingroſs al the hatred of the vulgar to whoſe thicker apprehenſions they are more ſuitable; yet that the iſſue of the iraſcible are brutiſh ſins too, both Scripture and reaſon do jointly teſtify.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles declare it not by way of diſcovery, or proof, but <hi>Enſtaſis,</hi> pointing at it as a thing evident, but unregarded. St. <hi>Iames</hi> 4.1. Asketh <hi>whence come</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Wars</hi> but from the inward? mens <hi>luſts war in their members</hi> and then draw the members of Chriſt to War among themſelves too. And St <hi>Paul Gal.</hi> 5.19. Reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109777:11"/>the quarrelſome ſins among the <hi>manifeſt ſins of the fiesh,</hi> as well as the laſcivious. And more plainly and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatically 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.1. The Greek Philoſophers would not admit young men to be fit hearers of their grave Lectures, as being yet in the ſecond region of life, the <hi>animal life,</hi> and unfit to be fed with <hi>rational diſcourſes</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til their judgements were better ripened, and the ſcumme of their youthful luſts &amp; paſſions boiled away: St <hi>Paul</hi> treateth the <hi>Corinthians</hi> according to their own principles, telleth them they are as uncapable of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of Chriſtianity as children of their Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal diſcourſes: for they were yet but <hi>ſenſual,</hi> their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections childiſh and brutiſh, uncapable of ſpiritual diſcourſes. <hi>And I brethren (ſaith he) could not ſpeak unto you as unto ſpiritual, but as unto carnal even as unto babes in Chriſt. I have ſed you with milk and not with meat, for hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ye were not able to bear it, neither yet now are ye able. For ye are yet carnal:</hi> And this their carnality he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth by their factiouſneſſe, as by a moſt undoubtable demonſtration; While ye are ſome of one party, and ſome of another are ye not carnal? Is it not moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that factious men are carnal men? Do not then pleaſe your ſelves in that humor as if it were an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of I know not what excellency, when it is a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt evidence of your ſenſuality: As well may a child pretend himſelf fit to command in an army, becauſe he hath gotten a fine Hobby-horſe, or to be a privy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller becauſe he hath a guilded Primer, as you can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend your ſelves to be good Chriſtians becauſe you ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate into parties. Thoſe <hi>gathered Churches,</hi> and <hi>purer ordinances,</hi> that <hi>ſeparation</hi> and <hi>non-conformity</hi> and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever other Phraſes the Spirit of faction delighteth to play withall, are but ſo many gaudes and the more you pleaſe your ſelves with them the more childiſhneſſe you betray. Untill you lay aſide theſe toyes, and betake your ſelves to the more ſubſtantial duties of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, <hi>Love and a ſound minde;</hi> however you may pride
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109777:11"/>your ſelves in a conceit of being higher Scholars in Chriſts Schoole, yet know you are not yet perfect in the very firſt and plaineſt leſſon, very babes, not come ſo far forth as to be ABC darians, mere animals (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) unable <hi>to underſtand the things of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>that are ſpiritually diſcerned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the ſame Apoſtle 1 <hi>Corinthians</hi> 3.3. proveth that their dividing themſelves into parties demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrateth them to <hi>be carnall and walk as men</hi> (or as the Syriack rendreth it <hi>to be bodily, and walk in the flesh) i. e.</hi> to be ſuch, as like beaſts attend onely their bodies and ſerve the fleſh; <hi>men</hi> in ſhape, <hi>beaſts</hi> in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</p>
            <p>It is not only the naſty <hi>ſow</hi> that trampleth <hi>pearls under feet</hi> which muſt be reckoned for a <hi>beaſt;</hi> the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relſome <hi>dog</hi> that <hi>flyes upon men and rends them,</hi> Wolves and bears; foxes and lyons are to be reckoned for <hi>beaſts,</hi> and ſo are all thoſe that <hi>bite and devour;</hi> So the factious man is <hi>ſenſual</hi> as well as the debauched.</p>
            <p>The good old <hi>Iacob</hi> ſeeing his ſons Coat torn, and bloody concluded it the work of ſome wild Beaſt; he was not much miſtaken, the cruel brethren were no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Nay they were much worſe, They were Divels: For ſtrife and envy is not onely ſenſual but</p>
            <p n="3">3. Diveliſh, and herein our Apoſtles brother St. <hi>Iohn</hi> agreeth with him 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.11. In this the children of God are manifeſt, and the children of the Divil, <hi>&amp;c. Cain was of the wicked one and ſlew his brother</hi> v. 12. and <hi>whoever hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his brother is a murtherer,</hi> verſ. 15. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> agreeth with both, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.26, 27. Let not the Sun go down upon your wrath neither give place to the Devil: let not your wrath ſtay with you till it fix into hatred, for hatred is a Devil the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth hatred.</p>
            <p>And ſurely <hi>hatred</hi> is directly oppoſite to <hi>Love; Intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance</hi> is only a <hi>ſtranger</hi> to <hi>love, hatred</hi> an <hi>enemy.</hi> The <hi>Atheiſt is without God,</hi> the factious man is an <hi>antitheiſt,</hi> an adverſary to him. Debauchery is <hi>unchriſtian,</hi> hatred is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109777:12"/>
               <hi>Antichristian, ſenſuall</hi> ſins are more <hi>palpable,</hi> but <hi>ſpiritual</hi> ſins are more <hi>odious:</hi> Thoſe are crude and groſs, theſe are diſtilled and Alcoliſated, not ſo maſſive but more miſchievous. Is it not worſe to be a <hi>Divel</hi> then a <hi>beaſt?</hi> Who ever ſaw the <hi>Divel</hi> drunk? or when was he taken in adultery. His debaucheries are of another region: he that hath no <hi>flesh</hi> cannot be guilty (I mean formally guilty) of the ſins of the <hi>flesh:</hi> his are properly ſins of the ſpirit: ſins of the body are but the body of ſin, the ſins of the ſpirit, are the ſpirit of ſin. And thoſe that will deſcribe the divel may as well be thought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe a ſchiſmatick.</p>
            <p>The Divel having no body cannot be deſcribed by bodily deformityes, it is not a black colour or a cloven foot, a horned forehead, or an ugly viſage, a long taile or hideous claws that can paint out his deformityes which are of another kind, but greater uglineſſe.</p>
            <p>Pride, malice, ſlandering, cenſoriouſneſs, envy, rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, &amp;c. Thus <hi>rebellion is as the ſin of witchcraft,</hi> maketh them of the <hi>Divels</hi> party in oppoſition to God. The <hi>earthly and ſenſuall</hi> are a kind of neuters in compariſon of malice, which carrieth men quite over to the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite ſide: This containeth all the wickedneſſe of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other and addeth greater of it's own. What one ſaid of ingratitude may better be ſaid of contentiouſneſſe. <hi>Call me factious, you call me all things,</hi> you call me thief, drunkard, whoremonger, nay you call me <hi>Devil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the <hi>works of the Devil</hi> which <hi>Christ came into the world to deſtroy.</hi> The Divel is the great make-bate, Chriſt the great peace maker. He would not come into the world untill there were a general peace over all its face, and as ſoon as he came the Angels came from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to proclaim <hi>peace on earth.</hi> He came and preached peace and that all evenues might be ſecured againſt ſtrife, he required us <hi>to love our</hi> very <hi>enemies.</hi> Love was his <hi>royal law,</hi> and we may ſay of it as <hi>Samuel</hi> of King Saul, <hi>ſee ye him whom the Lord hath choſen that there is none
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109777:12"/>like him among all the people.</hi> All the Officers of Chriſt are Ambaſſadors of reconciliation, their work is to <hi>edify the body in love,</hi> what are they then that preach conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion but <hi>meſſengers of Satan to buffet us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Divel can transform himſelf into an Angel of Light.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.13, 14.</note> But when he goeth to work diviſion, how is it that we do not diſcover him by his cloven foot? his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>transform themſelves into the Apoſtles of Chriſt, they come in sheeps clothing,</hi> but when they fall to worry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us, how is it that we do not diſcover them to be <hi>ravening Wolves?</hi> How hath our Saviour condemned the Spirit of pride, and ſeparation in the <hi>Phariſees!</hi> (the word <hi>Phariſees</hi> ſignifieth <hi>Separatiſts.</hi>) How have all the Apoſtles declamed againſt it in their rivals! how have all the ages and regions of Chriſtianity complained of it in their Heretiks, and eſpecially how have our ſelves ſmarted under it in the pretended <hi>godly party!</hi> How is it then that the moſt ſimple can yet be deluded by it, after ſo many warnings and ſuch frequent and wofull experience? Other ſins which are but ſenſual in their original, and not very prejudicial in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences brand the guilty with indelible infamy. Yet how impudently doth this <hi>ſpiritual wickedneſs in high places,</hi> plead not onely for indemnity but veneration! All other things are prophane, Churches and Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, and Church maintenance muſt reſigne all their Sacredneſs to theſe men: And all other ſins may, and muſt be puniſhed; but faction and diſobedience muſt be priviledged. To puniſh thoſe is neceſſary juſtice, to queſtion this is cruel perſecution. Thus the Pope ſent a check to <hi>Rich.</hi> 1. for making a priſoner of a Biſhop though taken in Battle, and required him to ſend him his ſon; but the King in ſtead of the perſon ſent the armour, adviſing his holineſs <hi>to ſee whether this were his ſons Coat.</hi> The Pope with ſhame returned anſwer that was not the Coat of any ſon of his but of ſome child of <hi>Mars:</hi> Contentious and Schiſmatical perſons are not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109777:13"/>the children of the Prince of peace but the God of War, and whoever would priviledge them from puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment might learn ſhame from the throne of impudence: What? muſt laws be to crimes, as of old they were complained to be, to perſons, like <hi>Cobwebs,</hi> which catch the ſmaller flies, and let the greater break through? For ſhame let's hear no more of that complaint that non-conformity, hath been more ſeverely puniſhed ſometimes then drunkenneſs, as if a Divel were not worſe then a beaſt. If we do not yet ſee greater odiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in this ſin, I hope at next ſtep we ſhall, when we conſider that as it is moſt baſe in it's Original, ſo it is moſt miſcievous in its Effects, and ſo moſt juſtly odious to God and puniſhable by man.</p>
            <p>As our moſt gracious God in the work of creation, aimed not at any ſervice the world could do him (his infinite happineſs, beeing uncapable to receive any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition from his creatures) but only deſired to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate himſelf and his happineſs: ſo in his government thereof, he provideth by his laws not for his own but his creatures good. Hence was it that our Saviour who came to bring us preſent as well as future happineſs, took ſuch great care to endeare love unto us, as being above all other graces, the greateſt promoter of our felicity: and hence is it that our Apoſtle the more to incenſe us againſt this ſin, doth not onely detect it for a cheater; but proceedeth to indict it as a notable malefactor againſt the peace of our Soveraigne Lord the Prince of peace.</p>
            <p>Thus we have ſeen this impoſtor doubly detected, by diſcovering the fountain whence he <hi>doth not,</hi> and whence he <hi>doth</hi> come. In the next verſe his indictment is laid in, by ſhewing the ſea to which he tendeth, a ſea of <hi>confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and miſchief;</hi> he is charged to be a malefactor of the higheſt degree, a notorious offender <hi>againſt the peace of our Soveraign Lord God, his Crown and Dignity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lawes proportion puniſhments, not alway to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:109777:13"/>the <hi>hainouſneſs,</hi> but ever to the <hi>miſchievouſneſs</hi> of the crime. A <hi>mutinous word</hi> in an army is puniſhed with death, becauſe it might draw on the ruin of the whole Army. What is <hi>mutiny</hi> in an <hi>Army,</hi> is <hi>ſedition</hi> in the <hi>State</hi> and <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> in the Church: It is therefore now to be condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the uglineſs and perniciouſneſſe of it's iſſue, as well as for the baſeneſſe of it's race. What ſin ſhall we ballance againſt this? What other ſin can be charged to bring <hi>confuſion and all kind of miſchief</hi> with it? If we look to the root, every others ſin is of ſome one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, this of all: other ſins hurt one or two this is an epidemical miſchief: Of what other ſin can it be ſaid, that it <hi>ſetteth on fire the whole courſe of nature, and is ſet on fire of hell?</hi> A ſingle murther is guilty of death, this butchereth multitudes in an hour, and maketh a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual trade of it. The <hi>whoremonger defileth</hi> (and doth but <hi>defile</hi>) two or three bodies, and <hi>begetteth</hi> a life unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully; This doth not <hi>defile</hi> onely, or <hi>beget,</hi> it <hi>deſtroyeth,</hi> and that by <hi>heaps upon heaps.</hi> The <hi>drunkard</hi> waſteth <hi>time and wine, and wit</hi> and turneth <hi>beaſt,</hi> this deſtroyeth <hi>lires,</hi> and turneth <hi>Divel.</hi> The <hi>thief</hi> and (analogically) every other ſinner may anſwer a <hi>factious</hi> man as the Pirate did <hi>Alexander Magnus I rob with one ship, thou with whole Fleets; I private merchants, thou whole nations.</hi> A Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matik cannot tell another of his <hi>mote,</hi> but he may be reproved for his <hi>beam.</hi> Could all the ſins in the world have brought ſuch a ſea of miſchief, as this hath done upon us? How many thouſand of families hath it ruin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? How many millions of lives deſtroyed? what trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of wealth waſted? What <hi>confuſion</hi> (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) what <hi>unſettledneſs</hi> in Church and State? And how much more then all this had we ſuffered if God had not wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid to it <hi>hither are the proud waves come, but</hi> ſhall paſs <hi>no further.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there are degrees, there is a <hi>Prince of Devils:</hi> This ſin though it be alway <hi>Divelish,</hi> yet ſometimes it is ſo in a higher degree. To ſtrive with an equal or inferior,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:109777:14"/>is wicked; but to ſtrive with a ſuperior, is much more ſo.
<note place="margin">Hoſ. 4.4.</note> The Prophet maketh it a ſymptom of a people de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperately wicked, and paſt all hope of reclaming when <hi>they ſtrive with their Prieſts.</hi> It was the clamerous fault of the Iſraelites that they quarrelled even with <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron:</hi> in whoſe perſons God himſelf is concerned, for <hi>he that reſiſteth the power reſisteth the ordinance of God.</hi> The <hi>Corinthians</hi> are warned that they ſhould not <hi>murmur as the</hi> Iſraelites <hi>did leſt they be deſtroyed</hi> like them. And <hi>theſe things ſaith he are written for our inſtruction.</hi> But we would not receive <hi>inſtruction. We murmured</hi> (would we had done no more) and <hi>were deſtroyed of Serpents,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The Brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe and the bulk, &amp;c.</note> things that crept among us out of obſcure holes, things of whom we know not the pedigree, nor ſhould have heard the name but for their venome: By ſuch <hi>Serpents</hi> were many of us <hi>deſtroyed,</hi> and many of us <hi>ſtung,</hi> and had been worſe if God had not provided a remedy.</p>
            <p>The ſin hath yet another aggravation. It is obſerved that <hi>they murmured at the ſea, even at the read ſea,</hi> even within the proſpect of ſo great a deliverance. It is but newly that God hath wrought ſuch another deliverance for us: The <hi>read ſea</hi> of a bloudy faction <hi>divided in to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> and gave us between them a <hi>dry &amp; ſafe</hi> paſſage to our liberty: ſo that without one drop of bloud we arrived at that happineſſe, which in our boldeſt hopes we could not have expected without a ſea of bloud and tears. And do we <hi>murmur</hi> at <hi>ſuch a time</hi> as this? a time which requireth to be ſpent in praiſes to God and mutuall congratulations?</p>
            <p>When the Iſraelites were reſtored from captivity, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8.10. commanded the people to <hi>eat and drink, and ſend portions,</hi> do we <hi>quarrel and complain</hi> at <hi>ſuch a</hi> time?
<note place="margin">Ionah 4.9.</note> This is an aggravation of <hi>Ionahs</hi> peeviſhneſs. <hi>Doſt thou well to be angry?</hi> Thou <hi>Ionah? Doſt thou well to be angry for thy goard?</hi> Haſt thou ſo quickly forgotten the <hi>ſtorm</hi> upon the ſea, and the <hi>Whales belly</hi> under it. How few, dayes is it ſince thou wouldeſt have given one of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:109777:14"/>thy eyes to behold the Sun with the other; and art thou ſo quickly angry becauſe it ſhineth a little too hot upon thee?
<note place="margin">Cha. 2 5.</note> How ſadly didſt thou complain that <hi>thy head was wrapt about with weeds,</hi> and art thou ſo quickly angry that a <hi>weed</hi> is withered over thy <hi>head: Angry</hi> ſo quickly? and ſo much? and for a <hi>weed</hi> too? A poor <hi>weed,</hi> the iſſue of the <hi>night,</hi> and the breakfaſt of a <hi>worm?</hi> ſo much anger for ſo ſlight a trifle, and ſo little pity for ſo great a city?</p>
            <p>You that are Miniſters, and you that profeſſe to love Miniſters <hi>Doe you do well to be angry for your covenant?</hi> Have you already forgotten what fears chill'd your hearts but a few moneths ſince? What would you not <hi>then</hi> have given to be aſſured of <hi>a King,</hi> and a Church upon any terms? When we groaned under the yoke which our former factiouſneſs had brought upon us, it was then the expreſſion of a chief of the <hi>Scotish</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, <hi>We ſee too late that we have buryed Monarchy and Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopacy in one common grave; but we would dig away the earth of that grave with our teeth to reſtore them.</hi> And do you gnaſh thoſe <hi>teeth</hi> for indignation that God hath reſtored them? And all this <hi>aenger</hi> for your <hi>covenant,</hi> a <hi>weed</hi> which ſprung up but laſt <hi>night,</hi> a night of <hi>confuſion</hi> and rebellion? Is the <hi>Scotish</hi> thiſtle ſuch a precious flower? Is it not a fretting prickly <hi>weed?</hi> doth it not fetch bloud where ever it cometh? No, No, it is not the loſſe of that rigid, troubleſome diſcipline that vexeth you; It is your <hi>reputation;</hi> You are afraid to be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>falſe Prophets,</hi> and to have made ſo loud clamors for <hi>nothing;</hi> you doubt leſt you ſhould be thought either to be <hi>timeſervers</hi> now, or to have been ſeditious heretofore, if you now ſubmit to that government which you <hi>ſet the world one fire</hi> to deſtroy: But is your <hi>reputation</hi> ſo conſiderable that the <hi>peace of the Church</hi> muſt be ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to it? Muſt ſo many thouſand lives redeem you from ſuch cheap fears? And do you <hi>well</hi> in this too? Is that <hi>earthly ſenſual, devilish</hi> ſin ſo inconſiderable in your
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:109777:15"/>eyes? Nay muſt it be <hi>juſtified,</hi> as if it were <hi>no ſin at all?</hi> Nay, muſt it be <hi>honoured,</hi> as if it were a piece of <hi>Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe?</hi> Chriſt made it the cognizance of his <hi>Diſciples, if you love one another,</hi> and muſt it paſſe for a mark of good Chriſtians if they be quarrelſome? Is it not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough that ſo great a ſin be <hi>connived at?</hi> muſt it be <hi>ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified too?</hi> Ambitious Devil! Is it not a favour to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpited <hi>from the Deep,</hi> muſt thou be <hi>worshiped</hi> too? <hi>Worshiped by the Son of God too?</hi> No leſſe command ſerve for a ſacrifice to the Devil, then the very critical com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt? No leſſe ſin ſerve him, then the <hi>devilish</hi> ſin of Faction; Me thinks he might be contented to be ſerved by the meaner ſins, and to be worſhiped as the God of this World: as <hi>Mammon.</hi> or <hi>Venus,</hi> by the ſins of <hi>covetouſneſſe</hi> or <hi>intemperance.</hi> The <hi>Groves</hi> and the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-place</hi> might have ſerved, and muſt he needs ſet up his Altars in the Temple of God? and deceive thoſe that come thither to pay their devotions? make them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that their affections are enflamed with <hi>zeal from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove,</hi> when they are <hi>ſet on fire of hell?</hi> He may now be contented to part with thoſe ſervices of the inferiour ſort, the debaucheries of the body, Drunkenneſſe and Fornication. But ſtay, muſt the Sword of Juſtice deſtroy none but poor and vulgar <hi>Amalekites?</hi> muſt the King be ſpared? yea, and royally attended too? muſt the <hi>fat cattle</hi> be kept <hi>alive,</hi> and that for <hi>ſacrifice too?</hi> And muſt this be called <hi>obeying the commandment of the Lord?</hi> Doth God give every Magiſtrate as large a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion againſt ſin,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.28.24.</note> as he did to <hi>Saul</hi> againſt <hi>Amalek, Go and utterly deſtroy the ſinners?</hi> And ſhall it be called <hi>justice</hi> to puniſh the <hi>vulgar,</hi> and <hi>perſecution</hi> to puniſh the <hi>King</hi> of ſins? Is not this to <hi>ſear the people, and obey their voice who judge by outward appearance,</hi> and are eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to honour the <hi>Devil, when he turneth himſelf into an Angel of light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is indeed the root of ſin and errour; we judge like Children by the outſide, take all for <hi>Gold that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109777:15"/>gliſters.</hi> This maketh us prefer the viſible happineſſe of this World: This made St. <hi>Paul</hi> complain that the falſe Apoſtles were preferred above himſelf, becauſe the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians judged by outward appearance, and ſo did not judge righteous judgement.</hi> But our preſent errour exceedeth all: Many eſteem the future happineſſe of heaven be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath the preſent enjoyments of the world, but no man condemneth heaven as a place of miſery: whereas in the reverſe we doe not onely reckon Faction to be a leſſe ſin then the more viſible ſins of the fleſh,
<note place="margin">Polano hiſt. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Trid</note> but we magnifie it as the very character of Godlineſſe. <hi>Never was better myſtery found</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>then to uſe Religion to make one inſenſible:</hi> But to uſe the greateſt of ſins for a token of Godlineſſe, this is the very <hi>myſtery</hi> of the <hi>myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we ſee what great reaſon the Apoſtle had, ſo importunately to <hi>beſeech</hi> the <hi>Romans,</hi> that they would <hi>mark them which cauſe Diviſion.</hi> I ſhall help you to know them by thoſe principles which they build upon, and wherewith they deceive the hearts of the ſimple, and maintain diviſion in the Church. I ſhall ſhew the Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars upon which Faction is built, It will not need <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon's</hi> ſtrength to pull them down; if you doe but <hi>mark them,</hi> you <hi>look</hi> them into nothing.</p>
            <div n="1" type="pillar_of_faction">
               <head>1. <hi>That we muſt keep as great a diſtance from the</hi> Papiſts <hi>as we can.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>This carrieth malice in it's very countenance, need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no obſerver to help you <hi>mark:</hi> and beſide, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of it, is ſo certainly falſe, that it is impoſſible to be true. For it ſelf is moſt exactly <hi>Popish,</hi> and therefore it is impoſſible to avoid <hi>Popery,</hi> unleſſe we avoid this very poſition, which ſaith we muſt ſo avoid it. <hi>Popery</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver came to it's full growth, untill the Conventicle at <hi>Trent,</hi> nor was this principle ever authentically practiſed untill then: There it was firſt authorized into a rule, that <hi>they muſt keep at the greatest diſtance from Hereticks.</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:109777:16"/>If we reform this poſition, as we have done the whole Religion, we may have this truth out of it. We muſt avoid all thoſe Doctrines which are truly <hi>Popish</hi> and <hi>falſe;</hi> yet not becauſe they are <hi>Popish,</hi> but becauſe they are <hi>falſe;</hi> and upon this account we muſt avoid theſe Doctrines: <hi>That we muſt shun ſome Doctrines and Practiſes, meerly upon this reaſon, becauſe maintained by Hereticks: That the King hath no power in Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call matters: That in ſome caſes the Subjects, may lawfully reſiſt the King: That all men are damned who are not of our Party.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe and the like poſitions we muſt avoid: not ſo much becauſe they are <hi>Popish</hi> (though indeed they be ſo, and Jeſuiticall too, the worſt ſort of Popery) as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are both <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>factions.</hi> But if we lay it down crudely, that <hi>we muſt neither do nor ſay as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts do, what shall become of our Religion?</hi> Muſt we turn <hi>Turks,</hi> or <hi>Iewes,</hi> or <hi>Heathens</hi> to avoid <hi>Popery?</hi> If we ſhould, yet muſt we retain ſome of their belief, unleſſe we deny a God too; Nay, if we drive home this princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, we muſt as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>go out of the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is by ſome of the <hi>Popish</hi> Writers made a character of the <hi>English Nation,</hi> that <hi>they think they are ſo much the nearer Heaven, as they are further from</hi> Rome: They have too much colour to ſpeak it of <hi>ſome,</hi> but they betray too much malice in applying it to <hi>all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the great difference between the Fathers of our Church, and the Children of diſobedience: the one would have ſuch a <hi>form of worship,</hi> as might invite the ſoberer <hi>Papiſts</hi> to communicate with us; the other would have either no <hi>form</hi> at all, or ſo ſlovenly an one, that the <hi>Papists</hi> may nauſeate it; the one would go as far as they may to meet the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> in hope that at leaſt the more moderate and unintereſſed of them, would go ſome few ſteps to meet us; the other will go as far from them as they can, that there never may be a meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Now <hi>Ibeſeech you mark,</hi> which of theſe two they are
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:109777:16"/>which cauſe diviſion and hinder union, and <hi>avoid them.</hi> Which of theſe beſt followeth the Apoſtles precept com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding us, <hi>If it be poſsible and as much as in us lyeth to live peaceably with all men?</hi> Which beſt imitateth his example <hi>that became all things to all men.</hi> He that <hi>to the Iews became as a Iew that he might gain the Iewes,</hi> would he not to the Papiſts become as a Papiſt, that he might gain the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt? It is no groundleſſe conjecture of an obſerving ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious perſon, that if the Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>England</hi> had been kept among the reformed in <hi>France,</hi> all the French would long ſince have turned Proteſtants: Their own Cardinal it ſeems is of the ſame mind, who ſuppreſſed the uſe of them, becauſe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple began to entertain more charitable thoughts of our religion, and he feared that at next ſtep they might preferre it before their own. It was wiſely done; the <hi>earthen pot</hi> ought to keep diſtance, but the <hi>braſen</hi> need not fear to come up cloſe to it: let them fear a meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, who diſtruſt their own ſtrength, to keep diſtance from the means of reconciliation is the figne either of an <hi>heretick,</hi> or at leaſt of a <hi>ſchiſmatick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And by this I ſuppoſe it appeareth how we ought to value that objection which is uſually made againſt our <hi>form of Common Prayer,</hi> That <hi>it is taken out of the Maſs-Book.</hi> If that be a ſufficient accuſation we muſt condemn our religion too. When the Papiſts ask us, <hi>Where our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion was before Luther?</hi> we have no better anſwer then to ſay, <hi>It was in their own:</hi> we fet it thence as the refiner: fetcheth <hi>metal</hi> out of the <hi>oar:</hi> We <hi>reformed</hi> from them by keeping the <hi>ſilver</hi> and leaving the <hi>drovs;</hi> we <hi>reformed</hi> the <hi>old</hi> did not <hi>make</hi> a <hi>new.</hi> It is ſo far from being a fault in our liturgy that it may be truly called <hi>Common,</hi> ſo <hi>common</hi> that all Chriſtians (Papiſts and all) may joyn with us; that I doubt not to reck on it among it's excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies, and I fear not to wiſh that the <hi>Popish Miſſal</hi> were ſo <hi>reformed</hi> that it might be lawfull for our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Merchants to communicate with them.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:109777:17"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſ.</hi> It may perhaps be thought ſufficient for an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to all this to ſay, <hi>That while we uſe ceremonies to draw on the Papiſts, we thereby drive away our own bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; we cauſe ſtrife at home, by endeavouring peace abroad, and ſo this very poſition must be marked and avoided as a cauſer of diviſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Phariſees were angry with Chriſt for eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Publicans, yet he thought a ſoul well pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed with a Phariſees diſcontent. The whole have no need of a phyſician; you think your ſelves ſuch, &amp; then there is no need of complying with you.</p>
               <p>And this is the preſent caſe: By complying with the Papiſts in ſome innocent Ceremonies, we may have <hi>hope,</hi> and therefore it is charity to <hi>endeavour</hi> to reduce them to the truth. You are <hi>angry</hi> and complain of <hi>Scandal.</hi> (By the way he that hath learned of the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable D. <hi>Hammond</hi> to underſtand what a <hi>Scandal</hi> is, will ſee that it is a flat contradiction to complain that I am ſcandaliſed: it is as if a man ſhould ſay he cannot chooſe but <hi>ſtumble at</hi> that, which he knoweth to lye in his way, that he cannot avoyd being caught in ſuch a <hi>trapp</hi> as he knoweth to be tilled for him: whereas the very formality of a <hi>ſtumbling block</hi> and a <hi>trapp</hi> do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in not being known.) And require that we ſhould be really ſcandalous to the Papiſts by tempting them to <hi>hate to</hi> be <hi>reformed,</hi> that you may not be angry with us for our deſire to ſave them. You diſobediently quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel at <hi>your ſuperiors</hi> charity; and to this diſobedience adde a falſe accuſation as if they brought in that ſtrife, which your ſelves have riſen.</p>
               <p>But can you thus father the diviſion upon the Church? Iudge by this caſe, Two families are at difference; The maſter of one of them out of love to Chriſt ſeeketh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with the adverſary, and uſeth means to procure it: ſome of his children obey him and joyn with him in ſo good an enterpriſe: others, that are more implacable, refuſe and make a faction among the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109777:17"/>and then declare the good man to be a litigious perſon, &amp; a raiſer of ſtrife among thoſe of his houſhold. This is the true ſtate of the quarrel, and I beſeech you mark them which are the true cauſes of the diviſion and avoid them.</p>
               <p>What puffing is there among ſome to blow up the old coales, and kindle our old ridiculous but tragical fears and jealouſies! What crying out that <hi>Popery, Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is coming in, Liturgy and Organs and Surplices,</hi> &amp;c. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Popery would come in apace, if once we grant it to be as ancient as thoſe things: We muſt no longer call it an innovation nor deny it our veneration: how quickly would Popery come in among us, if the ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical party could do the Papiſts ſervice in that work, wherein their endeavours are plainly united, the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of that government which all the Fathers of the Church but one venerate for Apoſtolical, and that one in his greateſt bitterneſſe againſt it acknowledgeth to have been inſtituted as a bulwark againſt hereſies, and theſe men would demoliſh as a piece of hereſy that their new diſcipline might be advanced. How aptly are theſe men ſaid to ſtand in the Church like the ugly Anticks in buildings: which with great ſhew of bend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſtraining pretend to bear up the weight of the whole fabrick, but are not thanked by wiſe men for the ſervice they do, ſo much as laught at for their falſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences and real deformityes. How much they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to the ſupporting the Proteſtant cauſe, witneſſe the Engliſh Nunnery at <hi>Antwerp,</hi> witneſſe the many ſporades both of Nobles and others that were tempted by our unſettledneſſe to think better of the boſome of the Church of Rome (though polluted) then of the wilderneſs peſtered with ſo many ſorts of fiery ſerpents: But how much that Epiſcopal party which they ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly call Popiſh have reſiſted the groweth of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, witneſſe the invincible armies of Jewels, Andrews, Fields, Potters, Ferns, Coſins, Bramhals, Hammonds,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:109777:18"/>Taylors, &amp;c. and eſpecially <hi>Laud</hi> and <hi>Chillingworth</hi> whom the ſchiſmaticks have done the Pope ſo much ſervice as to deſtroy, whereas if they had any true af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to the Proteſtant cauſe, the beſt of them might ſay to either of thoſe Martyrs as the people to David, <hi>Thou art worth</hi> 10000 <hi>of us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such Popery as theſe men &amp; many others either wrote, or died, or both, in defence of, ſuch Popery as flouriſhed in the firſt and pureſt ages of Chriſtianity, ſuch Popery as by the bleſſing of God, we were reformed to in the dayes of King <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. ſuch Popery as many zealous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons defended with their lives in the dayes of Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> that Popery for which <hi>Rome</hi> hateth and feareth our Church more then any other of Chriſtendom. That Popery which Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> would with all his heart have eſtabliſhed in <hi>Geneva</hi> if the place had been capable of it, that Popery which the moſt learned of the Outlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Reformed do ſtrongly wiſh and faintly hope for; That Popery God be bleſſed is coming in apace.</p>
               <p>The fable of the <hi>Fox,</hi> that was caught in a Gin by the tail and forced to bite it off and afterward perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the other Foxes to bite off their tails too under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, that they were both burthenſome and needleſſe, is a perfect reſemblance of our controverſy. But what if the Church of <hi>Geneva,</hi> were neceſſitated to maime her ſelf, and prevailed upon ſome other Churches to be her apes, and glory with her in their naked buttoks; but the Church of <hi>England</hi> would onely waſh, and cleanſe and flea but not maime her ſelf, reform her errors and ſuperſtitions without loſing that Government, which is ſo manifeſtly ancient, doth this deſerve ſo much cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor? Is our Church Popiſh becauſe it is governed by Biſhops? as well may the King be called a Fanatik be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he upholdeth vertue. But certainly whoever ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth any thing becauſe his enemy uſeth it, betrayeth a malicious ſpirit, and ſuch Doctrines deſerve to be <hi>mark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for cauſing diviſions among us.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="pillar_of_faction">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:109777:18"/>
               <head>2. <hi>That nothing may be brought into the worſhip of God, but what is warranted by the word of God, and to do it, is Popery and ſuperſtition.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>If they mean an <hi>Explicite and particular warrant,</hi> then this opinion pleadeth to be rejected as <hi>Popish, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious,</hi> for it hath no ſuch <hi>expreſſe warrant</hi> in the word, as it requireth. If they mean a <hi>general and impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite warrant;</hi> The Church hath ſuch an one 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order.</hi> This had been ſuperfluous if all particulars had been <hi>expreſly</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, and it had been too large if the Church were not a competent judge of what is <hi>orderly and decent.</hi> Me thinks if not his <hi>reaſon,</hi> yet at leaſt the <hi>authority</hi> of ſo judicious a Father as Mr. <hi>Calvine</hi> ſhould prevail in this caſe, his words <hi>ad literam</hi> are theſe—<hi>Quin etiam hinc col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligere promptum eſt, has poſteriores</hi> (viz. <hi>pias Eccleſiae leges</hi>) <hi>non</hi> eſſe <hi>habendas pro humanis traditionibus, quandoquidem fundatae ſunt in hoc generali mandato. Et liquidam approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem, habent, quaſi ex ore Chriſti ipſius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But my preſent deſigne calleth upon me not to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute but mark the cauſers of diviſion;</hi> and yet indeed the very <hi>marking</hi> of any Doctrine for ſuch is an abundant confutation. <hi>Mark</hi> then whether this doth not, and will not perpetually <hi>quarrel</hi> with any kind of <hi>worship,</hi> that ſhall be injoyned. Let us <hi>e. g.</hi> ſuppoſe it required that the two <hi>Sacraments</hi> ſhould be celebrated after their own new mode: That for <hi>Baptiſme</hi> a fine drilled frame ſhould be ſet up by the Miniſters Desk, and a baſon ſet in it, and that the Father ſhould come, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> May not their own queſtions be in this caſe demanded: <hi>What war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for this? did the Apoſtles ſo?</hi> &amp;c. Suppoſe again we ſhould be required to ſit at the Lords Supper. Might it not again be demanded <hi>whether Chriſt did ſo?</hi> The more unlearned may think he did. But it is manifeſt that they did not <hi>ſit</hi> but <hi>lye down</hi> to meat: and if we muſt celebrate that Supper after the ſame manner as Chriſt did, We muſt get an <hi>upper Chamber</hi> (and that a <hi>gueſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:109777:19"/>Chamber</hi> too,) and we muſt have beds ſet to lye upon round a table, and there we muſt eat a <hi>Lamb</hi> for Supper, Nay, we muſt remember that it is particularly deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by the Apoſtle as a ſignal circumſtance, that all this was done <hi>in the ſame night that Chriſt was betrayed.</hi> Muſt then the Miniſter be <hi>betrayed and crucified</hi> that all may be done after the Original form? where ſhall we ſtop? How ſhall we avoyd diviſion if this Doctrine ſtand? Do we not perceive that upon this principle we ſtill crumble into further ſeparation? Was it not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this foundation that <hi>the Quaker</hi> built his <hi>Fanatik Religion?</hi> The circumſtances being not ſo publikly known I ſhall here ſet them down, as I credibly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them from one that was preſent, and if I be called to it, ſhall name the perſon time and place. A com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Seekers being met, and ready to begin their prayers, One of them thus ſpake, <hi>Brethren what do we? We profeſs against forms, and we ſeparate from others becauſe they uſe forms: And do we our ſelves uſe a form.</hi> How to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void ſo manifeſt an objection they knew not, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore concluded to <hi>wait upon God,</hi> and expect how he would reveal his mind. They ſate ſilent all of them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt two hours, when ſuddenly a young women tumbled out of the window into the middle of the room, no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſigne of life appearing in her but this, a general ſhaking of the whole body; yet ſo, that every joint had a particular motion, and (ſo) impoſſible to be counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit. After much endeavour to recover her out of her ſuppoſed ſwoon, at length of her own accord ſhe roſe up ſaying that God had called her to ſpeak to them at that time, and that he would in the ſame manner conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to call thoſe that ſhould hereafter ſpeak to them. Iudge now what kind of ſpirit this was, which for a while did thus abuſe that frantick ſect and now leaveth them when growen of age to ſtand upon their own feet. Do you think it was the ſpirit of God which now break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the promiſe that then he made, and for a while per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed? If it were not, how can you think fit to lay that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:109777:19"/>foundation which if proſecuted will bring you to quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel with every <hi>form,</hi> but what the <hi>Divel</hi> ſhall ſhew?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="pillar_of_faction">
               <head>3. <hi>To neglect our own duty and look after the duty of others.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Is that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which the Apoſtle ranketh with <hi>malefactors thieves and murtherers;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.15.</note> for this reaſon doubtles, becauſe it weareth a ſtrong tincture of <hi>ſedition,</hi> but it is the uſual practiſe of nonconformiſts: who diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, not becauſe they <hi>may not obey</hi> but becauſe (ſay they) the Magiſtrate <hi>may not impoſe</hi> a form of worſhip. But what haſt thou to do to enquire after the Magiſtrates du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? let every man look to his own work. If the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate impoſe nothing that is ſinfull, it is <hi>lawfull</hi> and (if <hi>lawfull</hi>) <hi>neceſſary</hi> for thee to <hi>obey.</hi> It is at other times preached by the very ſame men that when any thing is required we ſhould ask this queſtion, <hi>Is it lawful? will it ſtand with my intereſt in God?</hi> But this is quite another queſtion, then to ask <hi>hath the Magiſtrate power to enjoyn this? might it not be better otherwiſe,</hi> &amp;c. When I read of the Iews wars with <hi>Antiochus,</hi> I read alſo of ſwines fleſh and Idolatry: When of their wars with the Romans, I read of Caligulae's ſtatue ſet up in the Temple, When I read of the burning of our Engliſh Martyrs, I find the worſhip of Images, Saints, and bread required. When I now hear talk of perſecution, of exhortation to loſe all and embrace the faggot rather then read the Common Prayer, I ſhould expect ſome great ſinfulneſſe in it, ſuch tragical exclamations would make a man expect news of a great image or a new religion ſet up.</p>
               <p>But <hi>when the accuſers ſtood up they brought no accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch things as I ſuppoſed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 25.18.</note> 
                  <hi>but had certain queſtions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it of their own ſuperſtition.</hi> (The word <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> critically ſignifieth a fear of what is good) The <hi>croſs in Baptiſm</hi> and <hi>ring in Marriage,</hi> ſome hymns <hi>ridiculous, prayers roped up like beads,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and in general to impoſe a form is but commanding luſty men to uſe crutches.</hi> Theſe and the like are the great objections, againſt which I now bring no other
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:109777:20"/>plea but this, <hi>they make nothing to the queſtion:</hi> The queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on truly ſtated is not, <hi>Whether it might be better otherwiſe?</hi> but <hi>whether it be ſinful,</hi> as it is. That excellent Martir <hi>Ridly</hi> that profeſſed he would <hi>rather preach in a fools coat then not preach at all,</hi> though he died for the avoiding a <hi>ſin</hi> would not have made a <hi>ſchiſm</hi> for the avoiding a <hi>Surplice.</hi> But this queſtion, <hi>Did the Governour well in making ſuch an order?</hi> as it carrieth a ſtrong favour of pride, ſo alſo a ſtrong tendency to ſedition. For if it be lawfull to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion (not the lawfulneſſe only, but the wiſdome of the lawes,) and to diſobey them whenſoever we ſhall be tempted to cenſure for the worſe; we ſhall never be free from ſedition as long as any man is <hi>proud or factious. It belongeth to a Dr.</hi> (ſaid Polano) <hi>to give a reaſon of his ſaying, A lawmaker if he do ſo, doth diminish his authority; becauſe the ſubject doth wreſtle with reaſon alleadged, and when he thinketh he hath reſolved it, he thinketh alſo that he hath taken all vertue from the precept.</hi> And Seneca more ſhort, <hi>Vt quis ſapientior legibus videatur, hoc ipſum eſt quod legibus prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur.</hi> Doſt thou think this <hi>no good form?</hi> Why <hi>this form</hi> was enjoyned for this very reaſon that it might not be in thee to judge <hi>what form is beſt. Go and learn what that mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth I will have mercy and not ſacrifice,</hi> &amp; thou ſhalt find that God requireth thee to prefer <hi>obedience</hi> and <hi>love</hi> above thoſe ſervices which better pleaſe thy fancy. It was <hi>Sauls error</hi> and his <hi>ruine</hi> that he did not what <hi>vvas commanded</hi> but what he <hi>thought better.</hi> Suppoſing then thou couldſt make a <hi>better form of vvorship,</hi> yet canſt thou not find <hi>a better vvay of ſerving God</hi> then by obedient conformity to the way of the Church. But granting more then u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually is, or reaſonably can be objected; That there were <hi>ſome things in the Common prayer Book truly ſinfull:</hi> Yet is it our duty to obey the Apoſtles precept: <hi>As much as in us lieth to live peaceably with all men.</hi> Let your <hi>peaceable mind,</hi> then appear by your <hi>conforming as far as poſsibly you can:</hi> Perhaps the clemency of the Fathers of the Church will induce them to wink at, if they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſatisfy your Scrupulous conſcience: however, this
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:109777:20"/>you ſhall gain, that you ſhall not ſuffer as <hi>malefactors:</hi> whereas if you willingly run upon <hi>faction,</hi> and trouble when you may without ſin avoid this, and cannot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin (and the greateſt of ſins too) practice that. Talk what you will of <hi>perſecution,</hi> you are but the <hi>Devils con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, and Martyrs.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="pillar_of_faction">
               <head>4. <hi>That the Law of man doth not binde the conſcience.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>That is, <hi>whenſoever a mans paſsions or intereſts shall tempt him, he may rebell.</hi> But admit the law of man did not <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly</hi> bind you, yet certainly it doth ſo <hi>by conſequence,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no other way to obey the <hi>royall law of Love.</hi> You know that <hi>Chriſt paid tribute,</hi> only that he might not give <hi>offence,</hi> though while he did it he demonſtrated that he was not bound to it. But ſay, doth not the law of man bind the conſcience? Doth not St. <hi>Paul</hi> tell us that <hi>he that reſiſteth the powers reſiſteth the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God?</hi> and <hi>therefore we muſt needs be ſubject, not only for wrath but alſo for conſcience ſake?</hi> And doth not St. <hi>Peter</hi> agree with him that <hi>we muſt ſubmit to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake?</hi> If the Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours had ſo pleaſed they might have rendred <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Humane invention,</hi> and then your own phraſe had bound you to obey. But as if it were a ſmal matter to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe themſelves <hi>not bound to obey,</hi> where the thing is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>indifferent;</hi> the contentious ſpirit carrieth ſome of them further; they profeſſe that in ſuch caſes they are <hi>bound not to obey;</hi> what they may do if they have liberty, they may not do if they be commanded. Is not this the true ſpirit of contradiction? the thing is lawfull in it's ſelf, put but a little <hi>obedience</hi> to it, and it becometh <hi>ſinfull.</hi> Thus <hi>rebellion</hi> is not only quitted of the <hi>ſin of witchcraft, devilishneſs;</hi> it is preferred and made <hi>the righteouſneſſe of the Saints, To kneel at the Communion,</hi> or <hi>ſay the Lords Prayer,</hi> &amp;c. is confeſſed a thing <hi>indifferent</hi> if it were not required, but being enjoyned it becometh <hi>ſinfull.</hi> But as liars are often entrapped in their own talk, ſo theſe men by over earneſtly defending their liberty, reneage it. Even thus
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:109777:21"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:109777:21"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:109777:22"/>they confeſs that <hi>humane lawes bind the conſcience,</hi> though to <hi>diſobedience.</hi> We muſt <hi>do</hi> what they <hi>forbid</hi> and <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear</hi> what they <hi>command.</hi> Had they commanded us <hi>to fit at the Communion</hi> we muſt have <hi>kneeled,</hi> had they forbad the uſe of the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> we muſt by no means have <hi>forborn</hi> it. I know a wiſe and good man whoſe wife had this humor to appear unwilling of whatſoever he deſired; yet he found a way to have her comply with his mind by making ſhew to deſire the contrary: muſt theſe men be thus managed? muſt the <hi>Law forbid</hi> what it would have <hi>done,</hi> and <hi>command</hi> what it would have <hi>avoyded?</hi> Would not a man think that theſe men came from the <hi>Antipodes,</hi> whoſe both <hi>Religion and Policy</hi> ſtandeth in ſuch <hi>direct opposition</hi> to that of our <hi>hemiſphere?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What God do they worſhip whoſe Faith is Faction, whoſe Religion is Rebellion, whoſe charity is mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering and ruining of Kingdoms? whoſe zeal is fury, whoſe order is confuſion, whoſe Chriſtianity, is anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, whoſe Godlineſs is Deviliſm? And what kind of Policy is that which armeth juſtice with a lath? ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Magiſtrates without power to command, and lawes without obligation to obedience, which requireth ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to puniſh the ſmalleſt ſins, and reverence the greateſt, and teacheth the ſubject to account the lawes obligatory only to diſobedience: which biddeth every man do what is beſt in his own eyes, and calleth lawleſneſs liberty. Which maketh it the duty of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject not to ſubmit his wiſdom to the law but to arraign the laws before his own fancy, and think himſelf not only free from obedience to it, but bound to oppoſe it, if he ſhall ſentence it, leſs wiſe then himſelf?</p>
               <p>Fanatik Schiſmatiks! There is this onely to be plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for you, that your <hi>principles are mad and</hi> therefore their <hi>wickednes is the more excuſable.</hi> And that God may therefore <hi>forgive you, becauſe you know not what you do.</hi> But ſure: <hi>This is not the wiſdom that cometh from above.</hi> Whatever hope it may have of Gods pardon it can have
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:109777:22"/>no title to our reverence. Let the Turks honour mad men and fools, as ſuppoſing them inſpired from above, but our Apoſtle preventeth this conceit in us toward fanaticks, for he concludeth his chapter with a character of heavenly wiſdom quite oppoſite. <hi>The wiſdom</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that is from above is firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle, and eaſy to be entreated, full of mercy and good fruits without wrangling, and without hypocriſy.</hi> Come now you that pretend your ſelves the ingroſſers of piety; that ſlight the phlegmatick dulneſs of the conformiſt, that go up to the Temple with the ſupercilious Phariſee, boaſting that <hi>you are not as other men are:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob 12.2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>No doubt but ye are the people, and wiſdom shall dy with you. But we have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding as well as you, we are not inferiour to you: yea, who knoweth not ſuch things as theſe?</hi> Who ſeeth not that this Apoſtle and all the reſt agree with their Maſter in teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing love to be the moſt Subſtantial piety? who ſeeth not that he multiplyeth the commendations of <hi>Peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs</hi> but paſſeth over <hi>Purity</hi> with one ſingle expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Who ſeeth not that (however you boaſt your ſelves not only the beſt Scholars, but the beſt Teachers in Chriſts School, yet) you ſtick in the firſt leſſon, and have not yet learned to take out a ſecond? And who ſeeth not that St. <hi>Paul</hi> challengeth it as ſelf evident that you have not learned the firſt, untill you be perfect in the ſecond? <hi>Are you not carnall whiles one ſaith I am of Paul and another I am of Apollo?</hi> Is not your very boaſted <hi>Purity</hi> impure untill you learn to be <hi>peaceable</hi> alſo? Alas! <hi>thoſe pollutions of the world through luſt,</hi> are but the Devils forlorn which it is a ſmall victory to overcome, his main ſtrength con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in his <hi>ſpiritual wickedneſſes,</hi> wherewith he deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth multitudes of ſuch as had <hi>eſcaped</hi> the other: and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny weak unwary Chriſtians become a prey to him, as the undiſciplined Barbarians did of old to the Romans: when having routed the Velites they broke their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders as to a purſuit and fell a cheap ſpoil to the legio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries: fleſhly luſt compared with ſpiritual pride is but
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:109777:23"/>as <hi>Saul</hi> to <hi>David:</hi> That hath ſlain it's thouſands, and this, it's 10000. Take heed of this Parthian though you have put him to flight, <hi>Think not that you have already at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, or were already perfect,</hi> as ſoon as you have learned to avoid the groſſer ſins of bodily uncleanneſſe: This is ſo far from making you perfect Chriſtians, that it doth not make you perfect ſo much as in your firſt leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; the wiſdome which is from above is firſt <hi>Pure,</hi> and it's purity <hi>cleanſeth from all filthineſs of flesh and ſpirit.</hi> On, on for ſhame then, to the next leſſon or the <hi>Publicans and harlots will enter into the Kingdom of Heaven before you:</hi> Their <hi>beaſtly</hi> ſins are but <hi>gnats:</hi> your <hi>Devilish</hi> ſins are <hi>Camels:</hi> you ſpy <hi>a more in their eyes, and behold a beam is in your own.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oh foolish ſeperatiſts who hath bewitched you, that you should not obey the truth ſo manifeſtly ſet forth,</hi> by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour and his Apoſtles, and all ages of the Church and your own dear experience? Is it the oſtentous garb of a boaſted zeal? <hi>This only would I learn of you,</hi> Do you think our Saviours invectives died with the Phariſees? or <hi>are they written for our ſakes?</hi> Is that worthy of reverence now, which was worthy of ſuch vehement reprehenſion then? What did our Saviour inveigh againſt in them, which their ſucceſſors do not glory in, and you adore as in defiance to our Saviours Sermons? They boaſted themſelves the only religious and thence concluded all men accurſed but themſelves and their diſciples; they wore exalted eylids and broad phylacteries and other pomps of profeſſed ſtrictneſs, that they might extract re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence from the deluded people: <hi>They made long prayers</hi> &amp; large profeſſions of zeal that they might <hi>devoure wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows houſes:</hi> and what more can you find in our modern Phariſees, but this that they out-ſin their predeceſſors? The Phariſees of old devoured widdows houſes: theſe make fatherleſſe and widdows, and then devour their houſes: they reverenced Gods Houſe that men might reverence them, theſe deny all reverence to Gods Houſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:109777:23"/>that they may ingroſſe it to themſelves &amp; <hi>take the houſes of God into poſſeſsion.</hi> And are not theſe the more <hi>ravenous wolves</hi> under the ſame <hi>sheeps cloathing?</hi> If we look to the Apoſtles, what did they complain of in their rivals, which is not reverenced in ours? <hi>Theſe</hi> as well as thoſe <hi>are falſe Apoſtles, deceitfull workers, transforming themſelves into the Apoſtles of Chriſt: theſe with fair ſpeeches deceive the hearts of the ſimple, and lead captive filly women:</hi> If we look to ſucceeding ages, was there ever any heretick in Church or rebel in State, that did not profeſſe for the glory of God and the good of man? But if we look back to our own miſeries, <hi>whence came wars and fightings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us,</hi> and whither had they brought us? Did they not come from a pretended zeal to reformation? and was it not a wonderfull providence that delivered us from to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal extirpation? And are we not bewitched if we can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſe into the ſame follies again, when a burnt child, though but a child, dreadeth fire, ſtrange power of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice. Is it not enough that our Saviour warned us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand by ſo many lively deſcriptions of our impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors? that the Apoſtles, and all ſucceeding ages, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, our own hath ſo evidently and ſadly ſuffered under their cheats? can we neither be forewarned by cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions nor afterward inſtructed by ſuch coſtly expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience? Can neither the leaves nor the very fruits tell us what they are? <hi>Do men gather grapes of thorns or figs of thistles?</hi> can love come from ſcratching thorns, or joy from prickling thiſtles? or could our Saviour have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed a plainer or ſurer way to know them then by their fruits?</p>
               <p>Let us judge them then by their fruits: <hi>The fruit of the ſpirit is joy, love, peace and long-ſuffering, gentleneſſe, goodneſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 5.22.</note> 
                  <hi>meekneſs:</hi> &amp; what is that ſpirit which is ſo fruitfull in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, miſeries, and contentions, &amp;c. Once more I beſeech in the words of St. Paul, <hi>to mark them which cauſe divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions among you and avoid them for they ſerve not the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, but their own intereſts and with fair ſpeeches deceive the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:109777:24"/>hearts of the ſimple:</hi> And I conclude as my Apoſtle doth this chapter, deſiring you to mark this too, <hi>that the fruit of righteouſneſs is ſowen in peace of them that make peace.</hi> That you may mark thoſe who promote peace and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and may follow them as wearing that mark, which our Saviour owneth for his.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>And the God of peace, and the peace of God which paſſeth all underſtanding, keep your hearts and minds in the knowledge and love of God and of one another,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:109777:24"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>The Author living at great diſtance from the Preſſe; ſome errours, eſpecially in punctations, have eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, the moſt conſiderable are theſe.</p>
            <p>Page 13. l. 7. Read <hi>So evident doth the Apoſtle account it.</hi> p. 14. l. 34. r. <hi>avennes.</hi> p. 16. l. 30. for thus r. <hi>For as.</hi> and l. 32. r. <hi>So in the next.</hi> p. 17. l. 10. r. <hi>other.</hi> and l. 33. for the r. <hi>thy.</hi> p. 18. l. 19. and 22. for read r. <hi>red.</hi> p. 24. l. 1. r. <hi>Obj.</hi> and l. 30. for riſen r. <hi>raiſed.</hi> p. 35. l. 18. r. <hi>Strange power of prejudice!</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
